AAYUSH SANJAY PRASAD

(857)-337-8175 / aayushsanjayprasad@gmail.com / LinkedIn | Github

A Software Engineer with a robust proficiency in Python, Java, and Data Structure & Algorithm Implementation, I bring a wealth of experience in system design, image processing, natural language processing, clustering, and cloud computing.

EDUCATION

Master of Science in Computer Science

Rivier University, NH, USA

Relevant Coursework: AI and ML, Robotics, Algorithms, JAVA Programming, OOD, OS, CS Fundamentals

Bachelor of Engineering Computer Engineering

Gujarat Technological University, Patan, India

Relevant Coursework: Analysis and Design of Algorithms, IoT, Data mining and BI, Database Management System

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming: C/C++, C#, JAVA, MATLAB, Python, HTML, CSS, Javascript, PHP, React.js, Node.js, SQL

Certifications: R language, Arduino, AWS Cloud

Python Libraries and Framework: NumPy, Pandas, TensorFlow, PyTorch, gTTS, PyAudio, pyttsx3, Django, Keras

Cloud Computing: AWS, Azure, Google Cloud Platform, Kubernetes

Competitions and Conferences: Smart India Hackathon 2017, Gujarat Industrial Hackathon 2018, AWS Cloud

EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant | Rivier University

September 2023 - May 2024

- Designed and implemented hardware setup, integrating motor drivers, GPS modules, and computer vision components for obstacle detection using OpenMV
- Developed Python-based modular software architecture to seamlessly integrate robot control, motor driving, and GPS navigation functionalities using **UART** for communication to achieve **a 62** % better performance
- Debugged and validated GPS navigation accuracy, obstacle avoidance effectiveness, and overall system performance in real-world environments through comprehensive testing by 15%

Software Engineer | Webyant, Deesa, India

September 2020 - April 2022

- Implemented a platform using **Python**, **Flask**, **RESTful API**, and **MySQL**, serving over 100k citizens and reducing paperwork by **85%**. Built scalable microservices with **SQLAlchemy** for database integration and deployed using AWS services
- Created user-facing features with ReactJS, building 50+ reusable UI components. Collaborated in Agile to integrate external APIs, increasing completion rate by 30% and reducing development time by 20%. Utilized JavaScript, HTML, and MySQL
- Conducted unit testing with **PyTest** and **Behave**, significantly reducing bugs. Configured **Flask-Admin** for monitoring health and performance metrics. Ensured seamless microservices integration and performance in an Agile environment

Software Development Intern | Desire Infotech, Gandhinagar, India

August 2019 - August 2020

- Constructed a program utilizing a combination of **Natural Language Processing (NLP)** with **NLTK** and **spaCy**, and machine learning algorithms with **TensorFlow** and **OpenCV**, allowing end-users to interact with screen using hand gestures via a camera
- Executed various features, such as voice assistance using gTTS and speech recognition, to increase productivity by 62%
- Increased efficiency from 10% to 78% by implementing different approaches to maintain sensitivity of the cursor, including adaptive thresholding and real-time data processing with **PyTorch** and **NumPy**

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Generative Adversarial Networks - Image Synthesis

- Designed and implemented computer vision pipelines for **object detection and recognition** using deep leaning techniques and managed and processed large datasets efficiently
- Preprocessed and augmented image datasets to reduce training time by ~70 %, utilizing libraries such as OpenCV and PIL and trained neural networks using Pytorch employing transfer learning and hyperparameter optimization
- Leveraged YOLOv5 for real-time object detection, customizing model for specific tasks and datasets
- Applied evaluation metrics like precision, recall, and mAP improving F-score from 0.76 to 0.82 to assess model

Minesweeper

- Conducted core game mechanics including grid generation, mine placement, and adjacent cell calculations using C++ data structures and algorithms to improve time spent while gaming by $\sim 60\%$
- Built a functional Minesweeper game in C++ with GUI, customizable levels, and strategic game logic using SFML
- Implemented event handling mechanisms to detect and process user input events and utilized SFML's event system to register callbacks and respond dynamically to player actions increasing response accuracy **from 55 % to 89.55 %**

Time Series Analysis

- Performed Time Series Analysis of monthly Sunspots from 1749 1983 with a Markov Chain
- Committed Autocorrelation and GoF test at 5% significance level to determine valid states of chain

Cloud-Based Data Analytics Dashboard

- Crafted cloud-based data analytical dashboard leveraging AWS cloud platform services, including AWS Glue for data ingestion,
 Amazon Redshift for data storage, and AWS EMR for data processing and analysis
- Constructed the frontend dashboard using React.js, with D3.js and Plotly for interactive data visualizations
- Integrated AWS Cognito for user authentication, ensuring scalability by implementing monitoring using AWS CloudWatch

EXTRA ACTIVITIES AND INTERESTS

- Circulation Assistant for Regina Library at Rivier University
- Vice President of Mozilla Group at Gujarat Technological University